this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software for software engineering
radio this is Robert bloomin I'm joined
today by Judy de Haan bootie is one of
the world's foremost experts on
service-oriented architecture and domain
driven design and also the creator of n
service bus the most popular service bus
for the.net framework booty along with
Greg Yuen is credited as co-founder of
the CQRS pattern and that will be the
subject of our discussion today Judy
welcome to software engineering radio
thanks for having me Robert it's a
pleasure being here would you like to
add anything about your background that
I didn't cover oh no I mean I I've done
a bunch of things in my career but I
prefer to keep it short and sweet okay
today we will be talking about CQRS that
is an acronym let's start out with what
does it stand for CQRS stands for
commend query responsibility segregation
we're going to go into that in more
detail I'd like to start out with the C
part command this refers to the well
known command pattern before we go into
the whole of CTRs would you please
review the command pattern briefly well
the idea of the command pattern is to
take the idea of let's say a task in the
system and represent it as an object in
its own right as opposed to merely
having commands appear as a methods on
some other object what could you tell us
a little bit about the history of sikhi
arts and how it got started
No okay so number of years back myself
and Greg young that we've we kind of
traveled in the same sort of circles he
has a blog I have a blog we read each
other we speak at a lot of the same
conferences and interact with online and
offline in sharing our experiences with
each other about the types of systems
we've been working on and the types of
problems the projects have run into we
found sort of a common theme of a
problems that a common approach that we
dealt with them where our general idea
was or maybe you started with the
general problem the problem we saw was
that often developers would use the same
set of objects both for commands and
their system as well as for queries and
that often that ended up in essence
pulling that set of objects in in two
different directions that it was really
difficult to come up with with just one
structure for those objects that would
be suitable for both handling commands
and queries so and each of us had tried
independently an approach where in
essence a different set of objects was
created for handling commands than the
set of objects that would handle the
queries and we both found independently
that that seemed to work out quite a bit
better and talking to each other we've
kind of verified our our approaches and
said you know this you should kind of
have a name this thing that it is that
we do and thus CQRS was coined you said
that having a different set of objects
for your rights and your reads helps out
how does that help out with a system so
to be clear this isn't for let's say
trivial data centric operations in a
system so what is often known as a crud
the create read update delete types of
behaviors which are
extremely data-centric take a bunch of
data store it in a certain table or read
it or delete it or update it if there
isn't very complex behavior and for
certain part of the system then it often
isn't necessary to apply CQRS approaches
however when you have either commands or
queries that are more complex in nature
queries that may require you to do more
complex calculations and pulling in
larger sets of data together commands
that have both complex validation and
business rules and and other not sure if
I use word side effects but other
additional behaviors that the trigger
further things happening in the system
later on it's in those areas where there
is sort that the highest inherent
complexity in the domain itself that
CQRS starts to make sense
and in those areas what we found is that
again queries are often operating on on
a very large data set they're doing
complex calculations but let's call it
the the center of gravity of how of how
queries are handled also in relation to
the staleness of data that a user is
willing to tolerate is very different
from when we're talking about command
processing when dealing with command
processing and you have similarly
complex logic neither the users or the
stakeholders tend to have any type of
sympathy for operating on scale data
that's when you know the really core
business logic is is being run it needs
to be executed on 100% consistent
up-to-date data and the results have to
be 100% consistent and up-to-date and on
the query side that's not needed as much
so
caching semantics and data staleness and
correctness of consistency stories are
very different between these two worlds
the commands of the query side of things
and as a result of that you know this is
just you could say applying the single
responsibility principle that instead of
trying to have one object or one set of
objects to both we choose to divide up
these responsibilities and have two
different sets of objects for it so the
essence of this pattern then is you have
different parts of your system which are
responsible for doing writes and
updating the single point of truth and
doing reads that may provide slightly
out of date data so maybe allow me to
refine that statement a little bit when
when looking at domains that have a fair
bit of complex logic we often see that
that there is some correlation in my
experience it's actually quite strong
with that domain being very multi-user
collaborative meaning that we have large
numbers of users that are both reading
and writing that same set of data at the
same time meaning that when one user is
looking at the results of a query
operation it is fairly likely that
another user has gotten in and performed
the command which changed the underlying
data meaning that user number one is now
looking at a stale picture of it so that
that element of of staleness around the
queries is a is a fairly significant
element of it in a multi-user
collaborative filming when you're
talking about this primarily the way of
breaking down responsibilities into
objects and I began reading about this
what I saw and and maybe I've picked up
a idiosyncratic view of what this is
about but a way of segregating load on
the system into different data
stores that might have different models
based on how those data stores are
accessed to what extent is is he curious
about distributing workload over
different data stores that are organized
differently so I'd say that it's it's
strongly correlated with that but that
it isn't necessary to go all the way in
that direction when you already have the
command part of your system that has to
operate on 100% accurate consistent
up-to-date information and you have the
query part of your system which can
provide somewhat stale results just that
element of staleness is indicative that
you could return information from a
cache now one could leave the cache as
being a purely volatile in-memory cache
or one could decide to actually make
that cache be a persistent cache in
which case the data structures the
persistent data structures behind that
persistent cache would end up looking
differently than the data structures
that are supporting the command side now
I tend to recommend that people evaluate
going down that path and being more
explicit in their data modeling of their
query needs independent of the data
modeling of the command means because
ultimately there's the other that the
data the persistent data structures are
going to have an impact on the kind of
objects that access those data
structures on top of them so if you want
to have a very clean highly optimized
command model you will have the most
ability to achieve that if you take more
complete control of the data structures
supporting those command objects and
designing it specifically for those
needs rather than trying to have a
single data structure that serves both
the command objects as well as the
objects ultimately this is taking the
principal or the approach of CQRS all
the way down into the data persistence
layer to give an example then a right
model might consist of a highly
normalized relational data store it
might be persisted to a highly
normalized relational data store which
is the most efficient data storage for
very fine-grained updates but read
models might be denormalized or
transformed into json or a format that's
closer to the consumers of that data and
requires less joining and reassembly of
normalized data structures so I say that
that's that's a very common way that
relational database technology is used
in systems that are applying the CQRS
approach that the command side remains
highly normalized in the query side is
highly denormalized than being said if
we were to take a step back and say is
really a relational database the most
appropriate solution either for the
command side or the query side what we
might see is that different domains have
a slightly different nature to them so
there might be some some queries that
are much more graph related so if for
example you look at recommendation
engines for example if you're on Amazon
purchasing a book they will show you
customers that bought this book also
bought these other books that is very
much a graph type of data structure with
many to many relationships between all
of these books and a certain kind of
ordering of how many people bought this
pair of books together versus that other
pair one could try to take that graph
set of data and
[Music]
denormalize that into a flat set of
tables in the database in a relational
database it probably wouldn't be as
optimized as they using a proper graph
database for it so and also on the
command side there are areas where if
you take a highly normalized set of
tables where you have a command whose
processing logic ends up touching
records across a large number of those
tables relational database technology
tends to escalate locks quite a bit more
aggressively the more rows and the more
tables that you have taking part in a
given transaction in which case it might
be more optimal to have and say a
document database structure or a
columnar store for certain types of
command processing that will result in
higher performance transactional
processing of those commands so
ultimately I see a very strong symbiosis
between no sequel databases and the CQRS
style of writing the logic on top we had
a show a while back about polyglot
persistence and this concept you're
explaining is very similar move maybe a
bit more of a overall vision of the
system on top of it to what we covered
on that show so I'd like to come back to
how from an infrastructure level the
different data stores remain consistent
I want to change directions right now
and talk about the relationship between
CQRS and domain driven design which
we've also we've had a show on domain
driven design tell us briefly what
domain driven design is listener to
you're more interested can go back and
listen to our show and talk about why
the close connection between those two
communities and are they is is you care
is really an extension of the
mein driven design or can you use it
independently as just a data
distribution pattern okay so there are a
bunch of questions and there hopefully
I'll remember them all if I don't I'm
sure you'll you'll leave me to the ones
that I missed so domain driven design in
my view is a a style of design that is
highly collaborative with a domain
expert meaning that there is someone
with a deep understanding of the
objectives of the business and the
nitty-gritty details of how things get
done someone who is able to effectively
make trade-offs between different ways
of implementing the same requirements
who is working hand in hand with the
development team in coming to a a
software design that reflects those
those business objectives most
effectively there are all sorts of
supporting patterns in this field of
domain driven design that have been you
know becoming more popular and less
popular over time for example the idea
of the repository pattern and the use of
object relational mapping technology
those have kind of waxed and waned over
time and the in the domain driven design
community but I'd say that the most
fundamental thing is having that very
strong connection between a a true
domain expert as opposed to say a
go-between like a business analyst who
interviews a domain expert for an hour -
and then structures the requirements in
some sort of whether that the use cases
or user stories or some other structure
and then in essence provides that to the
development team so I'd say that that's
probably one of the more important
elements of domain driven design as as
philosophy as an approach towards
building systems just getting those two
groups more closely together now and
again my view my interpretation of what
what is important in DDD now when we get
into CQRS
I find that one of the things that
connects very strongly to that is is
that idea of the command side in
particular focusing on let's call it a
task driven approach towards
representing requirements okay so
whereas some that's called more
traditional or older style of
development may have a user presented
directly with a large grid of
information where the user creates and
reads and updates and deletes various
records directly in other words the user
directly is doing data manipulation what
I found in my practice of domain trip
design and working with domain experts
is that often there is the idea of a
task a an identifiable set of behaviors
that fulfill some larger business
objective that a domain expert often
speaks about that if we represent that
both in the user interface as an
explicit thing as opposed to just
allowing the user to modify any set of
data that not only makes the users more
efficient in their usage of the system
it allows us to provide higher level
validation and better business rules
around those behaviors and that's where
the the CQRS
commands and the user interface centric
tasks and the domain driven design
business objectives
all line up so I'd say that that's
probably for me where where is the
strongest connection between CQRS and
dee dee dee is very much on on the
command side for the most part it's
having a domain experts beacon
task-oriented language as opposed to
data manipulation language and then
representing that both in the user
interface explicitly and then in the
underlying business logic again
explicitly through CQRS within domain
driven design there's a concept of they
called a bounded context I might call
that a subdomain or subsystem you're
talking about how commands are applied
to a given part of the domain within the
command processing logic clearly it has
to be operating on the most current
state that it's updating but could
command processing be reading from the
read models of other subdomains that it
uses for supporting data that is not
being modified by that command that's an
excellent question I get that question
frequently my general recommendation is
that a code that is in a given bounded
context or responsible for a given
subdomain should not be querying data
from from other subdomains the
specifically in when it comes to command
processing command processing is that
area where often the business requires
the highest level of consistency
guarantees as a result of that reading
from a somewhat stale of read model from
another bounded context is is going to
just work against that that needed
consistency the second part as I take
just gets back to a single
responsibility principle if
if you have identified subdomains
correctly and set up your your bounded
context or your your modules your your
set of object that implements the
requirements for a given sub domain well
then you should not need to query data
that way from from another sub domain
what can be a useful pattern in order to
propagate information from one sub
domain to another is the
publish/subscribe pattern meaning that
the code that is responsible for a given
subdomain when it makes some changes to
the data that it's responsible for it
can publish an event that would be
subscribed to by code and other
subdomains which will then store inside
them
the necessary subset of information that
they need whether that is for the
purposes of queries or for the purposes
of command processing but then we make
it quite a bit more explicit in so much
of thing this is an event this is what
it represents this is the this is the
consistency this is the this is how
up-to-date the data is that I'm giving
you
it helps developers think a little bit
more explicitly about things like the
the staleness of the data in their
system what I recommend developers do
anytime that they are applying the
publish/subscribe pattern is to to ask
themselves questions with regards to
call it the validity period of the data
that's being published so if I'm
publishing an event saying that a
customer status has changed that might
be something where I say okay the
customer is now a gold customer and
that's forever or it could be that like
a lot of loyalty programs that the
status is valid for one year and that if
you don't hear an event within that year
that refreshes that status then that
customer will lose that status so this
is not only useful for developers but
useful in the interaction with domain
expert saying anytime that I want to
propagate information from one subdomain
to another let's have a conversation
about the lifetime about the period of
validity of this information that we're
propagating across that will help the
code on the receiving end know what to
do with it how long to do with it and
and happen takes the business logic in a
slightly different direction
so ultimately these things are very what
these patterns support each other a lot
the idea of DDD subdomains
publish/subscribe event-driven
architecture approaches for getting
information from one subdomain to
another and then the CQRS code within a
given subdomain that is using
information from those events as a part
of its internal processing but let me
just reiterate I would strongly
recommend against having command
processing code in one sub domain
directly query data from another sub
doming got it at a high level we have
commands coming in generating updates as
they're processed
events that are published for other
subdomains we've also been talking about
multiple data stores that may run on
completely different types of servers
that are getting delayed versions of the
updates from command it sounds like
there's got to be some underlying
infrastructure that can move all these
events around between the different
subdomains and from the right model to
the read model what kind of underlying
is there an event bus or some kind of
messaging system that you would build
the CQRS distributed system on top of so
it's it's not at all coincidental that I
ended up creating
my own service bus technology it is
exactly for the reasons that you're
mentioning that that I had been doing a
lot of domain driven design CQRS type of
work trying to get to keep the order to
synchronize and propagate events between
sub domains that ultimately what I found
was that the Message Queuing technology
that I'd used in the past whether that
MSM queue activemq RabbitMQ etc the
messaging technology was was relatively
low-level and I always had to write a
lot of boilerplate code around the
messaging api's whether it be at the
level of transaction management whether
it be with regards to retry logic in
case exceptions occurred while
processing a message be that a command
or an event so after a number of years
of doing this I created my own and
started growing that organically and
that became an service bus I I do
recommend that developers that that are
moving in the direction of secures that
have divided up their code across a
couple of sub domains that are using
these publish/subscribe patterns do look
at using something above just a some
sort of messaging middleware but again
whether they create that themselves
whether they're using a free open-source
technology whether you they're using a
commercial technology there are a lot of
little nitty-gritty things to get right
and the challenge that I found was that
it's easy to get it wrong but to have
the wrong thing still appear to be
functional so if you get transaction
management semantics wrong when you are
running the system on your own machine
everything is going to work fine
you're really only going to end up
finding out you have consistency
problems when your system is under
relatively high load in production so
these sorts of latent faults in your
implementation can end up becoming quite
a bit of a headache when you have to
troubleshoot them in production so it
isn't trivial to to get all these little
things right definitely not something
that a developer that's currently in the
middle of implementing some really hairy
business logic for a very complex
requirement should be thinking about
they should have some some sort of
infrastructure there that gives them the
safe by default behavior when an example
of that be events coming into the right
model see realized
applied in a consistent way to the right
model which is updated it generates
events that go out to one or more read
models does each read model need to see
the events in the order that the
commands were applied on the right model
in order for the read model to get
updated correctly the answer to a
question like that is is it depends
there there is some logic on the read
side where it's quite possible that the
order in which you you do the processing
of these events doesn't matter there
could be other cases where the order
actually does matter so I'd before
delving too deeply into the the
technicalities of the it depends I want
to reiterate something that I said
earlier on which is that the difference
between crud style data manipulation
logic where I believe CQRS
adds more complexity than it actually
removes as opposed to those areas that
are much more task oriented and have a
fair bit of complex business logic in
them I've seen too many projects try to
apply a seek us on the crud data
manipulation
side of things and and end up with a lot
of difficulty over there one of the
challenges there that often occurs is
even for a single user so not
necessarily in the collaborative domain
but if just a single user updates record
and then updates the record again okay
so they change an address field and then
they change it a second time now if you
were to apply CQRS
let's say in a somewhat naive way where
the command signs say okay I've got an
update you know modify it publish an
event get another update modify the
record publish an event it is possible
that you would have on the read side two
threads that are processing those two
events in parallel in which case you
know it could be last one wins but you
don't really know whether the last one
is the right last one or it happened to
be the first one now developers have
come up with all sorts of techniques to
to work around this for example sequence
numbers that are passed in from the
client side when submitting these these
updates and then the read side which has
some some version checking behavior in
there so that so that it knows that it's
applying the events in the right order
when I see developers concerned about
the order in which things are being
applied it it makes me curious if they
are actually in a more crud data
manipulation type of domain where CQRS
is probably overkill and they should
just forget about the two different data
stores they should forget about cqs
having two different sets of objects for
the commands and queries and just have a
single normalized view just do
traditional ORM style data manipulation
on top of it and be done with it
so if you see that you're having issues
with regards to the ordering of things
for just a single user interaction it
could be that you are in a much more
crud data manipulation domain
in which case you should be using CQRS
to begin with by and large but now back
to the assuming that you are using CQRS
in the right place and the problem
domain justifies itself and now you are
concerned about the order in which
events are being processed that's an
area where I say before getting mired
down in the technical side of things
that's when you bring your domain expert
in and you need to have a conversation
with them because it could very well be
that these two events that are occurring
are as a result of two independent users
or two independent actors that have
submitted to different commands and now
the question is really should the fact
that one user submitted their command a
millisecond before the other or
millisecond after the other have such a
big impact on how things are processed
and potentially the requirements need to
be adjusted to to address this sort of
inherent concurrency in the domain
better one of the ways that that
manifests itself is by having what's
called clearer tasks or more granular
events that you don't run into the
problem of of concurrency in applying
them so I say first and foremost go back
to the domain have a discussion with the
domain expert understand the
collaboration and whatever conflict
semantics there are that are inherent in
that domain try to model that as
directly as possible without getting
bogged down in the technicalities of
event processing ordering and if you go
through all of that and you still have
an issue with the event ordering then
that would be a good time to apply
sequence numbers date time stamps on
your events and handle it at that level
there's another very commonly affiliated
pattern or architectural model that is
discussed on a lot
the CQRS boggs called event sourcing and
the event store talked about that and
the connection between event sourcing
and CQRS
mmm so greg young is is probably the the
best person to give the most
authoritative answers with regards to
event sourcing and specifically with
regard to the event store which is the
persistence technology that he created
in order to support the event sourcing
programming style so my view on it and
this is based on many interactions with
greg so i believe it to be a highly
accurate representation of the thing
itself event sourcing is a style of
implementing your business logic as well
as your data persistence such that the
current state of the data in your system
is not stored as is but rather the
series of deltas or interactions over
time that brought the system to the
current state is what is stored
okay so event sourcing to large extent
has a very strong statement with regards
to persistence
ergo it's very strong connection to
event store and the reason why Greg
ended up implementing the event store
ultimately he was creating a persistence
technology to solve or to address the
his approach to writing code in much the
way that I wrote and service bus in
order to address my need to do
publish/subscribe between subdomains so
you have this this style of persistence
where instead of storing the current
snapshot of the data of the system
you're storing the history of how we got
here in addition to that this is where
the event sourcing programming model
comes in because your your objects your
business logic
does not have the current state of the
data as it is right now what you do
instead is that the the objects are in
essence replayed that history of events
from either the beginning of time or the
last snapshot which brings them to a
current state and and then the new the
new action is applied to them so it is a
very it is a very focused way of both
dealing with history and current
interactions and and persistence that
all align together with each other where
one of the touted benefits of event
sourcing and events store as a
persistence technology when doing event
sourcing is that the system in essence
has a built-in audit log of everything
that happened which is very attractive
to a lot of people
however I'd state that the ability to
achieve a accurate audit log of a system
is you know it's equally accessible to
people that are not doing event sourcing
so if you're doing say just a
traditional rest type of API that is
using an or and behind the scenes to
talk to relational database you could
have some generic HTTP handling code
that every request that comes into the
system any HTTP action with the headers
and all of its bodies is persisted to
some data storage we're talking about
Message Queuing technology similarly
lots of Message Queuing technology has
auditing or sometimes they call it
journaling built-in so auditing is a
very good thing to have in a system
event sourcing and event stores also
provided but they're not the exclusive
providers of it my view
as to where event sourcing make sense is
similarly as I said before if you have a
crud data manipulation type of domain
neither CQRS nor event sourcing are
appropriate to apply to that part of the
domain so you want to be in a relatively
rich business logic task oriented kind
of domain another area so within that
category of problem domains that are a
fairly complex in nature I'd say that if
you have a domain that is highly time
oriented and insensitive to history so
I'd say probably one of the better known
domains that exhibits this sort of
property is that of payroll so when you
have bitemporal domains they're called
where there is the time at which
something occurred in this the time at
which was known in the real world and
that and that there's different
semantics around that so for example in
payroll you may have received a raise
three months ago and however it was not
actually recorded three months ago
you came to you found out a month too
late that the raise was not act was not
actually entered and that the money that
was deposited into your account was not
enough so you go back to payroll on the
company and say hey but I got this raise
I should have gotten more money in which
case what they will do is in essence
they replay history to say okay if you
had gotten the raise if the message
about giving you the raise had come in
at that time then we would have played
the payroll calculation this way
resulting in this much more money and
then that event that comes out of how
much more money you should have gotten
that feeds into this month's payroll and
then that's how we influence the
calculation so if you haven't
mean like that where this element of
replaying history is very core to the
business logic then I'd say a Venn
sourcing is a very good approach it's
extremely appropriate and it will
probably be much better than if you
tried to write that business logic
without an event sourcing type of
approach however if you have a domain
where most of the business logic is
really only ever operating on the
current set of data as it is right now
event sourcing is probably going to be
less optimal for you and that there is a
simpler way of writing that code okay
thank you for for that that was a
summary of event sourcing now I'll tell
you how I've understood the connection
between security and event sourcing and
tell me if if I've gotten it right the
commands come in they're processed in
your right or your command handle or
generates update events for the right
model which may generate further events
not propagated through the event bus or
event layer out to the different read
models the read models are replaying
events but they're transforming them in
a different way to produce appropriate
read models the read models are
therefore inherently derived data you
could if you wanted to let's say change
the data model of one of your read
models blow it away replay all the
events and have a new read model they're
ephemeral they're much easier to change
if you want a new type of search engine
or upgrade you could replay the event
trail into the new data store and all
the complexities of migrating state are
handled by this approach did I get that
right oh so I I disconnect some of what
you said just now from event sourcing
so first of all what you described is
you have the the CQRS part of it where
as a result of processing a command an
event is published and propagated over
to the query side which then processes
that event and updates a certain number
of read models that's that's just CQRS
or one style of CQRS where you choose to
have distinct data models for your
command processing side than your query
processing side okay you can absolutely
do CQRS
with just one data model in which case
you would not need to have an event be
emitted from the command side to go over
to the query side alright that's that
that's perfectly reasonable now the
second part of what you said with
regards to the read model the query side
saying that given that we have a audit
of all of the events that came into the
system we could replay that entire
history of events in order to create any
read model of our choosing okay that
allows us to discard a read model if we
want to sometimes greg mentions that
this is useful in the case where we had
a bug in our system and we ended up
showing the wrong data to our users
being able to go back in time replay
things correctly allows us to in essence
undo any incorrect things that were in
there I would however take that with a
pinch of salt and be very careful and in
talking to my domain expert and saying
if I showed incorrect information to my
users where this could be users or it
could be that this is information that
is exposed by any
ti2 other systems if we found out that
there was a bug in our system we would
be extremely careful in trying to track
down well which data was incorrect which
consumers had had received that
incorrect information what actions might
they have taken off of the back of that
incorrect information and in my
experience that's something that we tend
to do very carefully even before we
start thinking about rebuilding that
Reid model so that there are some
significant business ramifications that
need to be talked through and developers
shouldn't so quickly rush to a blow away
in quotes the existing rig model and
rebuild it from scratch every chance
that they get now again back to this
element of event sourcing versus
event-driven processing and the the
ability of having a built-in audit lock
the the history of all of the events
that came into the Reid model is
something that can be audited
independently of event sourcing okay
the event store persistence that Gregg
created has some very nice features that
make it quite a bit easier to to create
a new subscriber or a new read model
that consumes the audit history and that
is able to continue off of that audit
and process the regular stream of events
without any any code or configuration
changes to it okay so that is a that is
a very nice feature or style that is
used in the event store but that isn't
necessarily something that is directly
related to event sourcing
okay so the majority of what you
described is I'd say traditional CQRS in
nature much more so than event sourcing
in nature I know a lot of these things
end up getting mixed up all the time
it's a problem yeah okay so maybe I have
in my reading in my mind muddled
together or merged between CQRS and
event sourcing which solve different
problems can be used for different
purposes separately or together you are
covering this a little bit but just to
really if somebody like me came to you
and is experiencing this confusion what
uh what is it I might not be getting
about the difference between these two
and how to figure out whether I need one
or the other or both in my system
so I'd say the the biggest the biggest
missing piece in my experience is the
domain expert it's having someone that
you can actually put questions to so for
example that what I said yo is this a
domain where it is frequent for us to
have requirements where we need to in
essence replay history as a core part of
our command processing logic this is not
something that we as developers can
necessarily come up with ourselves so
something that domain expert can tell us
I like using the payroll example because
it's something that a lot of people who
are employed in companies have had
first-hand experience with and they can
understand the concept of replaying
events as a part of core business logic
okay
I'd say if you know take that example
get a real domain expert they can you
see in the coming six to twelve months
something in the domain that is
reflective of that that has that sort of
nature to it because if so then we
should be looking towards an event
sourcing model for these types of
objects and that will serve us well now
surrounding that there is probably going
to be some element of zqr s to it but I
wouldn't necessarily get overly tied up
with having a different query model that
comes out of that it could be that the
simplest thing to do would be to just
have the queries go off of the exact
same persistence technology as the
commands are processing and you know
probably 90% of the time that will end
up with a much simpler solution a whole
lot less code so I'd say start there in
terms of should I be applying event
sourcing I would say that there's a very
strong overlap and I mentioned this
earlier that you will tend to find a
good use of event sourcing in a domain
that has a great deal of command
processing complexity to of it meaning
that CQRS is already a good choice over
there and that this is not a very simple
standard data manipulation crud type of
environment okay so in that area I'd say
the in it also explains why there is so
much overlap and confusion between event
sourcing and CQRS because both of them
are applicable for domains with similar
complexity signatures as you will and
both of them are inapplicable in the
crud data manipulation domains okay does
that help yes thank you that does help
very much one other question I have
which is a bit tangential in looking at
the blogs and discussion groups around
CTRs it looks to have gained a lot of
traction in
the windows enterprise area and
Microsoft but not so much in the Linux
and open source world do you have any
thoughts on why that is so um I think
that it it started on the Microsoft side
because both me and Greg that was our
background with regards to it sort of
gaining popularity there to some extent
that that was driven off of myself and
Greg blogging about it and speaking at
conferences about it which were again
primarily conferences frequented by more
Microsoft developers than than those of
other platforms however recently I've
started to see a lot of interest from
the scala community and akka in
particular it with CQRS
and I'd say that there is a very strong
overlap with let's call it actor style
programming as well as functional
programming languages in that functional
programming languages tend to as an
approach have this style of programming
which is much more explicitly let's call
it command centric in nature which
allows them to be much better
parallelizable and get better
performance so I wouldn't necessarily
say that it is something that is only
applicable to the Microsoft stack I
think that there is that there are
certain elements of this pattern that
make it attractive to functional
programming or actor based programming
approaches which we're actually seeing a
whole lot more of not on the Microsoft
platform and CQRS is making strides
there as is a vent sourcing but to to
answer the
question as as to why why we haven't
seen that you use the term open source'
type of programming I differentiate say
use the term Windows Enterprise there
could equally be Java Enterprise and I
think that it's equally appropriate over
there but the I I don't see that there's
anything inherent about a open source or
even if it's non microsoft but still
commercial like an IBM and HP
environment that would make it not
suitable there because it's a just a
function of lineage me and Greg kind of
starting in that area nothing more if
listeners would like to learn more about
CQRS what are some of the resources out
there that you recommend well I take
definitely my blog Budi dehang comm UDID
aham calm there's Greg Young's blog I
don't remember off the top of my head
the URL we'll put that in the in the
show notes there are a bunch of other
people that have been blogging also
about CQRS and event sourcing and all
those styles I'd yeah and you have read
a bunch of the those blogs as well and I
mean you've gotten confused to some
extent as to where CQRS ends off and
where event sourcing begins and those
kinds of things so I am somewhat
hesitant to 22.2 to the other ones
Microsoft a while back did a CQRS
journey project that is something if
someone is a Microsoft developer that
can be interesting interesting set of
documents to read not so much it being
an authoritative source of information
of CQRS but as a kind of case study of a
group of people that tried to apply CQRS
to a domain
and the challenges that they uncovered
in the process specifically for them it
was applying it in the cloud the whole
issue of the need for supporting
infrastructure versus rolling your own
on on an as-needed basis was one of the
conclusions that they came to in that
Microsoft project that actually a fair
bit of infrastructure is extravagant
rying to re-implement the wheel it's
very time-consuming and difficult to do
right and of course the both both myself
and Greg teach on the topic of CQRS
and domain driven design for people that
want to learn more about domain driven
design in general and I strongly
recommend that I think that a very good
division of subdomains and bounded
context is extremely useful I might even
go so far as to say necessary to apply
CQRS well so learning more about domain
driven design ultimately go to the
source go to Eric Eric Evans you know
take his classes read the book Vaughn
Verne and recently has released a put
out a book called implementing domain
driven design also some very good
information in there so I'd say there's
no shortage of information out there on
CQRS
the big thing that I that I reiterate
from what I said earlier get access to a
domain expert someone who can make
meaningful trade-offs around the
definition of the requirements work with
them to divide that big domain into
smaller sub domains that requires
practice ok it's not just reading it
requires a fair bit of practice then the
more you do it the better that you get
at it the more your intuition develops
towards finding these sorts of
boundaries
and absolutely like I said you know go
to training my course Greg's course in
terms of supporting infrastructure
there's Greg's event store persistence
technology that's that get advanced or
calm and that's multi-platform by the
way and there's my in-service bus
technology which you can find at
particular net as well as a whole bunch
of other tooling around the service bus
that helps modeling and designing and
debugging these sorts of systems to be
quite a bit easier so that's what I was
very Judy you just now gave me the whole
show notes everything there will be in
the show notes you mentioned your blog
and service bus if listeners would like
to follow your thoughts are there any
other places that you publish to or
write to that you'd like people to check
out no I I primarily or when I find the
time to blog then I'll be blogging at
hoody dehang calm there's also the
particular net blog but if anything that
would just be sort of a cross post okay
well I duty thank you very much for
speaking to software engineering radio
oh it was my pleasure thanks so much for
having me thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by I Triple E software magazine for
more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website @ SC - radioman to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on itunes mention a message us on
twitter at se radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under the Creative Commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]